<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preacht at the funeral of Mr. Thomas Lamb July 23, 1686 by Richard Lucas ...</title>
            <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12986464</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12986464</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96203</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96203)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 719:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preacht at the funeral of Mr. Thomas Lamb July 23, 1686 by Richard Lucas ...</title>
                  <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lamb, Thomas, d. 1686.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XVII, 4-5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96203:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preacht at the FUNERAL OF Mr. Thomas Lamb <hi>July</hi> 23. 1686.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD LUCAS M.A. Vicar of St. <hi>Stephen's Coleman-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Smith</hi> at the <hi>Prince's-Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:96203:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 24. 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Hen. Maurice R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo Canl. à Sacris.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96203:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend Mr. JOHN LAMB Rector of <hi>Wheathampſted</hi> in <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough I expect this Sermon ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred by two ſorts of cenſures; Firſt, of thoſe who Envy that goodneſs which they will not imitate; and for the Vindication of their own worthleſneſs and barrenneſs, detract from the Excellence and Fruitfulneſs of others: Next of thoſe, who may be diſguſted at the courſeneſs and heavineſs of it: Yet this could not diſcourage me from the publication of it: For as to the former, if they could deſerve my conſideration, I am ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fortified againſt 'em by being conſcious to my ſelf, that I have impartially follow'd ſtrict Truth, either perſonally known to me, or abundantly atteſted; As to the latter I think verily, they do me no great wrong, for I agree thus far with em, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is by no means equal to the ſubject: But in this I have this comfort, that thought it can give no Luſtre or Dignity to the ſubject, it may receive
<pb facs="tcp:96203:3"/>both in ſome meaſure from it, and ſo may prove uſeful in deſpight of it's flatneſs. Beſides, Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this nature ought not to be ſtifled or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, as being ſuch excellent Vindications of our Chriſtian profeſſion, ſuch brisk reproaches and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing reproofs of the Coldneſs and Irreligion of evil men, and ſuch excellent Incentives of Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the good. And yet after all this, I think ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, I ſhould never have ſuffered this diſcourſe to have ſeen the Light (ſuch was my value for it!) had I not been over-rul'd, as you know, by the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſuch, whoſe Friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip I have no ground to queſtion, and to whoſe Judgment, I have juſt ground to pay a deference: Now that it is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht, it doth of Right belong to you; to whom I offer it, and intreat you to accept it, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it's imperfections; as a teſtimony of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for you, and of my kindneſs for the Memory of your dear Father, and my dear Friend departed, I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Affectionate Friend, and Humble Servant RICHARD LUCAS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96203:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 17.4, 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I have glorified thee on the Earth, I have finiſht the works which thou gaveſt me to do.</p>
                  <p>And now O Father, glorifie thou me with thine own ſelf, with the glory which I had with thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World was.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NOthing can afford ſo much comfort and ſupport, in the day of Calamity or Death, as the Conſcience of a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent Life; a faithful diſcharge of our Duty, being the Sole-Rational proof of our <hi>ſincerity,</hi> and our ſincerity being the only ſolid ground of <hi>Hope,</hi> and <hi>aſſurance</hi> towards God. <hi>If our heart</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> our Conſcience) <hi>condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God,</hi> 1 John 3.21.</p>
            <p>This is a Leſſon our Saviour has taught us by his own Example here in my Text; very well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96203:4"/>knowing that the time of his Death and Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion was very near at hand, that he might fortifie himſelf againſt all the Terrours of it, by confirming and ſtrengthening, <hi>his Hope of that Joy that was ſet before him,</hi> he enters up on a ſurvey of his paſt Life, recollects all his performances, reflects upon his Actions, and calls himſelf to an account concerning the Diſcharge of that <hi>Truſt</hi> which God had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him, of the great <hi>Work</hi> which he had undertaken for the Salvation of man, and the Honour of God: And finding upon a juſt and Impartial Reflection that he had through the whole courſe of his Life, acquitted himſelf faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and vigorouſly, his Soul rejoyceth within him, and he breaks out into expreſſions of holy <hi>Confidence</hi> and an aſſur'd and earneſt expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Reward</hi> of his Obedience and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. <hi>I have glorified thee on the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And now O Father, glorifie thou me with thine own ſelf,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus I have in part explained the words al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, having given you an account of the Occaſion, Deſign and Tendency of them: As they belong properly and peculiarly to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, they imply two things.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96203:4"/>
            <p>Firſt, His Faithful Diſcharge of his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Office; <hi>I have glorified thee,</hi> &amp;c. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted eſpecially— 1. In publiſhing the will of God to the World, as he himſelf explains it more fully in the following part of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. — 2. In the proof and evidence he gave of his Commiſſion from God, and the Divinity of his Doctrine, which was, the <hi>Wonderfulneſs</hi> of his works, and the unparallel'd <hi>Sanctity</hi> of his Life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His Expectation of Reward, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the exaltation of his Human Nature, and it's admiſſion into a participation of that Glory, which he enjoy'd with the Father from all Eternity. <hi>And now O Father, Glorifie thou me with thine own ſelf, with the Glory which I had with thee before the World was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if we conſider that Chriſt is the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's great pattern, that his Life is propos'd to us, as an Example to our Obedience, that his peace and joy is in ſome degree the Portion and Bleſſing of every faithful Diſciple, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of his, and that laſtly his exaltation and Glory is the Original and Idaea, by which our's ſhall in it's due proportion be form'd and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled, I may very well be allowed to interpret
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96203:5"/>the behaviour of our Lord in my text as an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſet us all in general, containing matter of Inſtruction and Advice to all Chriſtians, which may be reſolv'd into theſe two Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. <hi>That there is a Work given every one of us to ſiniſh,</hi> a Duty preſcrib'd each of us by the Conſcientious performance of which, <hi>we may gloriſie God on the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. That a Chriſtian's Comfort and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in Death, if rational, ought to flow from the Conſcience of a faithful diſcharge of this Duty.</p>
            <p>§ 1ſt. <hi>That there is a work,</hi> &amp;c. The Duties of human Life are of two ſorts — <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſuch as are common to all as <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians.—Secondly,</hi> ſuch as are proper and peculiar to ſome men as engag'd in diſtinct <hi>Callings</hi> and <hi>Profeſſions</hi> As <hi>Men</hi> and Chriſtians, Sobriety, Purity, Truth, Juſtice, Charity, Meekneſs, Long-Suffering, Devotion, Faith, Self-Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Obedience, and ſuch like are the works which God hath pre-ordain'd that we ſhould walk in: Theſe are Reflections and Raies of the Divine glory, theſe are the Tracks and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of the Divine Image, theſe are the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96203:5"/>and true Excellencies of a Chriſtian, in compariſon of which, the Celebrated Exploits of the Heathen-Gods, <hi>Jupiter, Hercules, Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> &amp;c. are, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaks, but child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh braveries, the blind Sallies of an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent paſſion, of an Unballaſted Impetus: By the conſtant and ſincere practice of theſe, we exalt and perfect our Natures, advancing them into a nearer participation of the Divine Image; by the conſtant and ſincere practice of theſe, we procure the peace, the ſecurity, the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and Proſperity of human Society; And finally, by the conſtant and ſincere practice of theſe, we adorn the Goſpel of Chriſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Honour of God, and <hi>ſhew forth the praiſes of him who called us out of Darkneſs into his Marvellous Light;</hi> for nothing does more convincingly manifeſt and publiſh to the World the Honourable Notions we entertain of God, the Purity and Power of our Chriſtian Faith, than a Life imploy'd and ſpent in theſe works; for by this we openly proclaim to the World, that we do not believe that a Holy and good God can be pleas'd with any thing but Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Goodneſs, or that any Sacrifice can be ſo acceptable to him as the Imitation (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96203:6"/>to our power) of his Divine Perfections.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe Duties common to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, there are others which flow from our diſtinct Profeſſions and Callings; Every man's Calling, whether he be a Paſtor in the Church, or a Ruler or Officer in the State, whether he be a Trader, Phyſician, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly exact ſome diſtinct kind of Vertue; As Watchfulneſs in Paſtors, Integrity in Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Juſtice in Traders, Tenderneſs in Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ſuch like, and in <hi>all,</hi> Induſtry and Diligence: Nor doth it a little import the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Religion, and the welfare of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Society, that every man do faithfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the particular and diſtinct Duty of his Calling; nor can he neglect it without invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelf in the guilt of trampling under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot the moſt powerful obligations; for <hi>this,</hi> the abilities God endow's him with, <hi>this,</hi> the truſt God commits to him; <hi>this,</hi> the Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies others have reaſonably fixt upon him; <hi>this,</hi> the general Covenant ſuppos'd entred into by every Member of a Community, that he will be uſeful and helpful in his place; <hi>this,</hi> the Intereſt of the publick, and the glory of God loudly calls and preſſes every man to; it being
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96203:6"/>impoſſible, that Decency and Order in human Affairs ſhould be preſerv'd, that the Beauty and Harmony of Divine Providence ſhould be maintain'd, that the mutual wants and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Mankind ſhould be miniſtred to, and ſupplied, or the Honour of God ſupported and upheld in the World, unleſs men be faithful in the diſcharge of the Duties of their ſeveral Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Profeſſions: This is that the Apoſtle exhorts to, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8. <hi>Having then gifts differing according to the Grace that is given to us, whether Prophecy, let us Propheſie accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Proportion of Faith; or Miniſtry, let us wait on our Miniſtring; or he that teacheth, on teaching; or he that exhorteth, on Exhortation: He that ruleth,</hi> let him do it <hi>with diligence</hi> The ſame Faithfulneſs and Diligence men are elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in Scripture exhorted to, in their ſecular and Prophane Callings.</p>
            <p>You ſee then what the works are which God preſcribes us to walk in, namely, the works of our general Callings, as we are <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;</hi> and the works of our diſtinct Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as we are dedicated to different imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Church or State. You diſcern in the next place the natural Bent and Tendency of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96203:7"/>theſe works towards the glorifying God on the Earth. This, then is the Poſt which you are to make good; this is the ſtation you are to fill; this is the Province you are to adorn; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe acquit your ſelves with a good Conſcience towards God or Man. And hence it follows—</p>
            <p>§ 2dly. That the Faithful diſcharge of our Duty is the only Rational ground of our Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance towards God. 'Tis true and confeſſed on all hands, that the Death and Merits of Chriſt is the great cauſe of our Peace and Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God; that through him, through him alone, all Chriſtians are to expect the pardon of their ſins, and the acceptance of their performances; That when <hi>we have done all, we are unprofitable Servants:</hi> And that the moſt unblameable and pious Life that ever was yet led upon Earth (except that of Chriſt's himſelf) could never be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the Teſt, the Tryal of God's ſtrict Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And therefore our Deceaſed Friend, notwithſtanding the nature and number of his good works not eaſily to be parallel'd (though I wiſh they were) by many Inſtances in this Age, gave us this ſhort account of his Faith
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96203:7"/>and Hope the day before his Death, <hi>I truſt in the mercy of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though all this be true, 'tis all nothing to the point in hand; for though Chriſt dyed for <hi>all,</hi> yet <hi>all</hi> have not a like or equal ground of Hope: Tho the Death of Jeſus be ſufficient to attone for the ſins of <hi>all,</hi> yet <hi>all</hi> are not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally pardoned: The Queſtion therefore is, what gives men a good Claim and a juſt Title to the Benefits of Chriſt's paſſion; and what is the cleareſt proof of the goodneſs of our Claim? and then nothing is more evident than that this is a faithful diſcharge of the Duties of Life, <hi>a finiſhing the works God gives us to do.</hi> Theſe are the proper effects of ſaving Knowledge, and a ſaving Faith; Theſe are the very Eſſentials of Repentance towards God; Theſe are the kindly Operations of Love unfeigned; Theſe are the proper tokens of the Divine preſence, and the Reſidence of God's Spirit within us; Theſe laſtly are the natural and genuine fruits of an enligthned underſtanding, and renew'd mind: Theſe therefore are the beſt proofs and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of our claim to all the Benefits of Chriſt's Death and Merits, and conſequently the moſt Rational Foundation of our Peace and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96203:8"/>in our Latter end. This is evident from the Examples of all Righteous and good men, whoſe Comfort in Death is wont to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portiond to the Piety and Sincerity of their Lives; hence (not to multiply Inſtances) that of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſht my Courſe, I have kept the Faith; henceforth, there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day; and not to me only, but to them alſo that love his appearing.</hi> Here we have the confident expectation of a Crown, but 'tis a Crown of Righteouſneſs; and if we examine the ground of this confidence of St <hi>Paul,</hi> it is, that War which he proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly waged, thoſe conflicts which he had ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully maintain'd againſt the World, the Fleſh and the Devil; his Indefatigable Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Race of Vertue and Goodneſs ſet before him: And finally, his ſtedfaſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken adherence to the Faith of Chriſt, in deſpight of all the malice and fury, with which he was aſſaulted.</p>
            <p>Thus have I briefly inſiſted on the words of my Text, as reſerving room for that which is a more fair and lively Comment on it, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96203:8"/>Life of our deceas'd Friend. And here in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of my method, I ſhould be obliged to begin with an account of his behaviour, in his particular profeſſion; but having reſolv'd to ſay nothing, but what I either perſonally know, or have full and unqueſtionable proof of, I will paſs over this part of his Life, as that to which, I am in a great meaſure a ſtranger; though I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear recommending to you two Rules, which he thought neceſſary for the Chriſtian Conduct of Trade—<hi>Firſt,</hi> That Traders ſhould carefully avoid the graſping at, and embracing ſo much buſineſs, as ſhould make their Trade encroach and intrench upon their Religion, that they ſhould not ſuffer their time and their hearts to be engros'd by the love and purſuit of Worldly gain, to the neglect and ruin of their Eternal Intereſt.—<hi>Secondly,</hi> That they ſhould propoſe and deſign an Increaſe of their Charity in proportion to the Increaſe of their Wealth. And now I proceed to the Life of our departed Friend, with regard to the general Obligations he lay under as <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> wherein we meet with theſe two things conſiderable, <hi>His Religion towards God, and his Charity towards Man.</hi> Theſe two divided and ſhared his whole
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96203:9"/>Life between them, there being very few Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it which might not be referred to the one or other, as the ſource and Principle of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Of his Religion towards God.</hi> This was that to which he dedicated and devoted himſelf betimes; <hi>He remembred his Creator in the days of his Youth;</hi> Nor was he more early than conſtant in this, for he perſiſted ſtedfaſt in it to the end; his Religion had no Interruption, no Intermiſſion; I could never find that there was any the leaſt period of his Life, which he abandon'd and gave up to an Indulgence of ſin and folly. 'Tis true, as you all know, he was ſometime miſled in point of Judgment; but 'tis as true that under all the changes of Times and Opinions, he retain'd his Sincerity and his Zeal: An Opinion of greater ſtrictneſs of Life, and a more lively reliſh and ſavour of ſpiritual things amongſt thoſe of the ſeparation firſt tempted him out of the boſom of our Church: and a deep ſenſe of the manifold Impieties and dreadful miſchiefs which attended ſeparation firſt mov'd him to return to us; for this rais'd many ſcruples and perplexities in him, and made him reaſonably doubt that God could not be the Author of that way. The method he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96203:9"/>afterwards took for a full and juſt Information of himſelf; namely, impartial Examination of our beſt writings, conference with our Ableſt men, together with inceſſant prayers to God for the Illumination of his Spirit, the time and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his Return, his open acknowledgment of his errour, his publick profeſſion of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, his ſolemn and earneſt Invitation of others to return to the paths of Truth and Peace, and his ſucceſsful Induſtry in recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe whom he had been Inſtrumental to pervert, ſufficiently demonſtrate the Sincerity and Integrity of his heart: And thoſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Treatiſes he has writ for the diſabuſing thoſe of the ſeparation, have made an abundant Compenſation for the Errours he was betray'd into through frailty &amp; weakneſs of Judgment.</p>
            <p>But I come now to his Religion, ſuch as it was ſince I knew him; and ſo I'le ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his own perſonal behaviour towards God, and of his zeal to propagate the fear of God among others.</p>
            <p>As to his own behaviour, the Character of the Godly man in the Pſalmiſt was truly his. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the Counſel of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of ſinners,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96203:10"/>nor ſitteth in the ſeat of the ſcornful. But his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light is in the Law of the Lord, and in his Law doth he meditate day and night, Pſal.</hi> 1.1, 2. He was a man that did abominate all Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wherein any thing was either ſaid or done to the diſparagement of Vertue, or Diſhonour of Religion: He was ſo far from partaking in the guilt of any ſuch thing, that he never wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the courage to reprove and rebuke it: And as all filthy and ſinful Communication was an Abomination, ſo all trifling and unprofitable Communication was a burden to his Soul: And therefore it was, that his Converſation was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd within ſo narrow a compaſs, that he had very few Confidents and Intimates, and very little Company beſides that of his near Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and the Poor; this he was with regard to Negative Righteouſneſs. As to poſitive Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, it may be truly ſaid of him, that <hi>his delight was in the Law of the Lord,</hi> whether this be to be inferred from meditation or practice, this could not but appear to every one that convers'd with him, for he was richly furniſht with Scripture Knowledge, he had treaſured up the richeſt Portions of Divine Writ, he had digeſted them into nouriſhment and ſtrength,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96203:10"/>and he was grown ſo familiarly acquainted with them, that there was no Doctrine of Faith, or Duty of Practice, for which he could not readily urge ſeveral the moſt pertinent Texts of Scripture, and not only cite the words, the Chapter, the verſe, but give a very Rational ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Spirit and deſign of them, and of their coherence with the Context. But his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, though it was, as it ought, begun and founded in <hi>Knowledge,</hi> yet it did not, like that of many men, terminate &amp; end in it too, but was perfected and finiſhed in <hi>Practice</hi> He was wont to place all Religion in three things, <hi>Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Adoration</hi> and <hi>Imitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, that of <hi>Contemplation,</hi> which is to the other two, like Oyl to Flame that nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes and ſupports it: You may gheſs by his Knowledge in Divine things, that he was no ſtranger to it. However one thing there is which deſerves to be recommended to your Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is this; after long experience, his Soul was grown weary of fruitleſs Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Barren Controverſies, and his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations were of late wiſely confined to theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Subjects, the purity and holineſs of God, the riches of his Love and goodneſs to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96203:11"/>manifeſted in Jeſus, and the bleſſedneſs of a future ſtate, into which laſt, he was very late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more particularly and Induſtriouſly inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, beginning ſeveral diſcourſes with me on that Subject, and carrying 'em on with no little Pleaſure and Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Adoration,</hi> he complained, I confeſs to me, that of late he could not put up his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with that Vigour and Importunity, with that cloſe Application and Intention of Spirit which he had formerly done; but withall he added, that as to one part of <hi>Adoration</hi> that of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, his Soul did abound in that, and he ever found himſelf exalted and lifted up in that Exerciſe. This part of Adoration he was wont to account as a maintaining Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Heavenly Inhabitants, and a joyning with the Church triumphant in their Hallelujahs. Upon which ground, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the purpoſe and devotion of his heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God in reſpect of his Faith, Love, and Obedience continued ſtedfaſt and unmoveable, I was inclin'd to impute the Alteration he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of, not to any abatement of his ſincerity or zeal, but to the heavineſs of his Age, and the Decay of his Spirits.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96203:11"/>
            <p>As to <hi>Imitation</hi> of God, he conceived that to conſiſt mainly in <hi>doing good,</hi> of which I ſhall ſay ſomthing preſently under the head of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, having firſt, according to the Order I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, taken notice of his zeal in propagating the fear of God amongſt others, which was no leſs eminent in him than the Piety of his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour towards God. He never let ſlip any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity either of reproving and diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing vice, or of preaching up and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending vertue, and this he did with that gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and authority, and with that Goodneſs and Charity, with that Evidence of Scripture back't with ſtrength of Reaſon and Experience, that he ſeldom miſſed of doing ſome good by it. He was extreamly Solicitous to inſtruct Youth in the Principles of our Religion, for which purpoſe he had a Catechiſm of his own compoſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the grounds of our Chriſtian Faith, which he did induſtriouſly imprint not only on the memories, but judgements and hearts of young people he did often inculcate the neceſſity and uſefulneſs of Writing Sermons, and repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing em at home; he did often bewail the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Converſation, and recommend the advantage of gracious and good Diſcourſes in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96203:12"/>our daily and familiar Entercourſe with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: he was zealous for the obſervation of Family-Duties, and in all this was eminently exemplary himſelf: His Reſolution was that of <hi>Joſhua, Chap.</hi> 24.15. <hi>As for me, I and my Houſe will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Nor can it be unknown to many here how ſucceſsful he was in this, what a ſpirit of Religion and Goodneſs reigned in his Family, and what laſting impreſſions of both, his endeavours made in his Children; and were it not that I ſhould oppreſs their Modeſty, and incur (it may be) an imputation of flattery which I deteſt and ſcorn, I would inſiſt more largely upon this Topick, as a Noble encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the watchfulneſs and Induſtry of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Maſters over their Children and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: from this his Charity to the Soul, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. To that which relates to the External ſtate of man; this was the ſecond thing propoſed to be ſpoken to, after his Religion towards God, <hi>His Charity towards man.</hi> This was that in which he conceived the Imitation of God moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to conſiſt, he was alwaies wont to have in his Mouth that of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, But let him that glorieth glory in this, that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96203:12"/>and knows me that I am the Lord which exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Loving kindneſs, Judgment and Righteouſneſs in the Earth; for in theſe things I delight, ſaith the Lord, Jer.</hi> 9.24. This therefore was the Vertue wherein he was Eminent and Exemplary; to this he ſo wholly gave up his Heart and his Life, that I may ſafely ſay, he did in ſome degree renounce his own buſineſs and his own Intereſt, that he might with leſs diſtraction and better ſucceſs attend the Concerns of the poor and miſerable. 'Tis true, (that I may her antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the Objection of ſome ſort of men) the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rities</hi> he undertook and engag'd himſelf in, were too many and too great to be carried on upon his own ſingle ſtock or particular fund; he had therefore aſſiſtance many waies; and much from many good men, I believe, here preſent: but 'tis as true too, that he was not only a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Steward and diſpenſer of other mens Bounty, but alſo bountiful himſelf even to the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his eſtate. To go on therefore to the point, ſeveral Hundreds of Priſoners were by him, with great travail and expence ſet free; Nay, Priſons themſelves were ſet free from ſome op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and cheats that had obtain'd in them, and rendred more hoſpitable and tolerable to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96203:13"/>the miſerable Inhabitants Fees being reduced to a Lower rate, and Maintenance and Proviſion for Priſoners much better ſetled: ſeveral entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled eſtates were by his care, prudence and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour clear'd and preſerved: Many deſolate <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans</hi> found in him the tenderneſs and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Father, and many deſolate <hi>Widows</hi> the Care and Protection of a Husband: How ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and liberal he was to very many Relations that ſtood in need of him, is well known to many here. Finally, ſuch Numbers of Poor were relieved by him, that he was continually throng'd by flocks of his Clients, (as he called them) and he could ſcarce paſs any ſtreet where the Bleſſings of ſome one or other ſuccour'd by him, did not light upon him. Nor did his Charity exert it ſelf only in the Relief of the poor and needy, but alſo in miniſtring to every ſort of neceſſity and miſery of mankind; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted the afflicted, reſcued the oppreſſed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed and counſelled the Ignorant, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the Obſtinate by the ſweetneſs of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, by the meekneſs of Reaſon, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Spirit of Religion, which diſcover'd it ſelf in all his Diſcourſes: In Sum, what <hi>Job</hi> ſaid of himſelf, may be with truth applied to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96203:13"/>this good man. <hi>I deliver'd the poor that cried, and the Fatherleſs and him that had none to help him: the bleſſing of him that was ready to periſh came upon me; and I cauſed the Widows heart to ſing for joy. I put on Righteouſneſs, and it cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me; My judgment was as a Robe and a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem: I was Eyes to the Blind, and Feet was I to Lame; I was a Father to the poor, and the cauſe which I knew not, I ſearch't out, and I brake the Jaws of the wicked, and pluck't the Spoyl out of his Teeth, Job</hi> 29.11, 12, &amp;c. Here I ſhould have concluded with this general account, were there not in his <hi>Charity</hi> three things ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently and peculiarly remarkable, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve never to be forgot, his <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> his <hi>Induſtry,</hi> and his <hi>Delight in doing good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt. His <hi>Meekneſs.</hi> He had a Text to this purpoſe which he did often repeat, <hi>Let it not grieve thee to bow down thine Ear to the Poor, and to give him a friendly anſwer with Meekneſs, Ecclus.</hi> 4.8. And he liv'd up to this Rule; no ſourneſs or churliſhneſs of Speech, no impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or inſolence of Behaviour did ever imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Alms or Relief to the needy: <hi>Charity</hi> was not a greater Ornament to <hi>Him,</hi> than his <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs</hi> was to his <hi>Charity:</hi> He
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96203:14"/>would often hear not only tedious and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, but alſo rude and paſſionate diſcourſes, with matchleſs Patience and Goodneſs, having regard to the miſeries, not the frailties of thoſe who addreſſed themſelves to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His <hi>Induſtry.</hi> He had often in his Mouth that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Bleſſed is he that conſiders the Poor,</hi> and that of <hi>Job</hi> juſt now ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>The cauſe that I knew not, I ſearch't out:</hi> And accordingly he did with indefatigable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſound the depths, and fathom the bottom of every cauſe; and when he did with great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitude and earneſtneſs of mind, ſtudy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive and conſult what method was moſt likely to prove effectual for the redreſs of the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and when he had fixt upon it, he ſet his heart ſo much upon the accompliſhment of his deſign, that there were ſeldom, if ever, any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties ſo great, which he did not one way or other remove or ſurmount: And he never thought much of the time or Travail which he beſtowed thus: So intent was he upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collent works of Charity, that he purſued them panting, and almoſt breathleſs; and I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times heard him regret the weakneſs and Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of his Age, and expreſs his Fear, leſt he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96203:14"/>ſhould live to thoſe years, wherein, through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of ſtrength, he might be utterly uſeleſs. Indeed, his decayed body was not at length able to undergo all the drudgery which ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and conſiderable deſigns of Charity did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; and therefore, for ſeveral his laſt years, he maintain'd a Servant on purpoſe to receive and execute his Directions</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One paſſage under this head I forgot in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, and it deſerves not to be omitted in the Preſs, which is, that he was often adviſed and preſſed to go into the Country for his health ſake; againſt this, he urged many ſcruples, which though they appear'd not to others of ſufficient weight, yet he could never bring his mind to it;</hi> What ſhall my Poor then do? ſaid he, 'tis even beſt for me to dye in my Station and in my Imployment.</p>
            <p>Such was his Vigour, ſuch his Induſtry. And God was pleas'd to bleſs him with ſuitable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; ſo that 'tis not eaſy to expreſs his <hi>Felicity</hi> in mollifying the moſt obdurate Creditors, in reducing them to terms of Moderation and Charitable compoſition, in reconciling diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and in ſweetning the moſt alienated and exaſperated minds.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, His <hi>Delight.</hi> It was one of his dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96203:15"/>Propoſitions which he ſet a high rate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That the Life of Man is to be eſtimated by the uſefulneſs of it;</hi> and accordingly that porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Life was always moſt delightful and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable to him, wherein he was moſt ſuccefully active in ſome deſign of Charity; his Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiced within him, when God had bleſſed him in the accompliſhment of any good work; and I may confidently ſay, that never Souldier en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd Victory, or Trader the increaſe of his Wealth with a truer ſatisfaction than he did the ſucceſſes of his Charitable Labours. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that taking notice, how much he was pleas'd with reflecting upon and repeating him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſeveral of his atchievements, and with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ecchoes and rebounds of them from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I grew ſometimes jealous of him, leſt <hi>Dead Flies</hi> ſhould corrupt this <hi>Oyntment,</hi> and a ſilly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Praiſe and vain glory ſhould blaſt his Charity, and bereave him of the Fruit and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of it; but upon narrower Inſpection into the Root of this matter, I found that this ſprung from the pleaſure he took in the Comfort and Happineſs which he procur'd to others: his pious Soul, as it did ſuffer in the miſery, ſo did it exalt in the Proſperity of his Brother, as he was ready
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96203:15"/>to <hi>weep with thoſe that wept,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>to rejoyce with thoſe that rejoyced,</hi> and ſo much the more when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God had made him the Inſtrument of their Joy, ſo that it was not his own praiſe that creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Satisfaction, but the good procur'd his Neighbour, and the honour which did from thence redound to God.</p>
            <p>Shall I now after all, add his Juſtice, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and Diligence in all his dealings and undertakings? His Simplicity and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, his Ingenuity, Meekneſs and Humility in all his Converſation? His Plaineſs, Sincerity and Zeal towards his Friend, ſhewing it ſelf eſpecially in his tenderneſs for his Eternal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt? The ſweetneſs and obligingneſs of his carriage, not towards his Children only, but even towards the meaneſt that had any Relation to him? Shall I add his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Moderation, and Comprehenſive Charity, for all peaceful, humble, and upright Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of every perſuaſion? Shall I inſiſt upon his Purity and Heavenly mindedneſs, not only to an Indifference, but (I may almoſt ſay) even Contempt for the things of this World, Wealth, Power, Honour, and the Oſtentation of Life? Shall I finally remember his Strictneſs and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96203:16"/>which was ſuch, that I had much ado to remove ſome Scruples out of his mind about the uſe of ſuch things, as I judg'd neceſſary to the ſupport of his age, and the maintenance of his health and ſtrength? Theſe and other Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of our deceas'd Friend, I might inſiſt upon, and in all this, I ſhould have the teſtimony and approbation of all that knew him: But the time would fail me, and I have ſaid enough, enough to do right in ſome meaſure to the memory of this Excellent perſon, for the <hi>Righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting Remembrance;</hi> enough to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter unſpeakable comfort and ſatisfaction to his Relations, and enough, I hope, to excite and ſtir up all that hear me this day to the Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this good man's Vertues, eſpecially when we ſhall add the conſideration in my text, that this will fortifie us againſt all the Terrours of Death; this will give us comfort and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the approaches of it. Then ſhall we be able to aſſure our ſelves <hi>that we are the Children of God,</hi> when we imitate his goodneſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, as he doth, in the works of Mercy and Charity: Then ſhall we be able to aſſure our ſelves that we are the true followers of Jeſus, when we are led by the ſame ſpirit, when we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96203:16"/>
               <hi>glorify God upon Earth, and finiſh the works which he has given us to do:</hi> And then ſhall we be able to lye down in the aſſured expectations of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reſurrection. This was the happy ſtate of this excellent man; Death was his Meditation, Death his Expectation; and when he met it, he met it with a chearful and ſerene ſoul; the Laſt words I had from him when I bid him my laſt farewel on <hi>Sunday,</hi> were, <hi>You and I ſhall meet again in another World, I do not queſtion it at all.</hi> Ah! that we could all live ſo as to have no fears, no doubts about eternal Life when we are come to dye! O think of the bleſſedneſs of ſuch a ſtate! and then remember that this aſſurance ariſes from the conſcience of a well ſpent Life, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a faithful diſcharge of our ſteward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip can enable us to meet God with comfort, and give us an Inheritance with Saints in Glory, and enrol us amongſt the Spirits of Juſt men made perfect.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
